Register of the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership (1931: Washington, D.C.) Records, 1931-1932 XX396
Hoover Institution Archives
President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership (1931: Washington, D.C.) Records
1931-1932
XX396
Hoover Institution Archives
51 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 oversize photograph (22.8 linear feet)
Memoranda, reports, correspondence, pamphlets, clippings, press releases, and expense statements, relating to housing conditions in the United States, and to proposals for improving them, and especially for promoting home ownership through home loan banks.
President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership (1931: Washington, D.C.)
Access
Microfilm use only.
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (49 reels).
Historical Note.
The Conference on Home Building and Home ownership was announced by President Hoover on August 30, 1930. It followed the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection as the second in the series of social studies to be undertaken by the administration. Its primary purpose was to bring together facts concerning housing throughout the United States; to determine the factors that influence housing, favorably or unfavorably, and how they are inter-related in cities, in smaller communities, and in rural areas; to focus attention upon the problems of home ownership and to suggest means of meeting them.
The President named Secretary of Commerce Robert P. Lamont and Secretary of the Interior Ray Lyman Wilbur as co-chairmen of the Conference. Dr. John M. Gries, who had organized and for several years headed the Division of Building and Housing in the Department of Commerce, was appointed Executive Secretary. A planning Committee was set up to advise and help with the organization.
The President and his advisers believed that the best way to get at the facts was to organize into study committees outstanding individuals engaged in one way or another in activities affecting housing. Thirty-one committees were formed and set to work in the course of 1931; of the 31, twenty-five were fact-finding committees, and six were correlating committees assigned the task of drawing from the 25 main committee reports recommendations related to: Technological Development; Legislation and Administration; Standards and Objectives; Research; Organizations Programs; Education and Service.
More than 540 individuals served as volunteers on the study committees. Funds for research in preparation for the Conference and for publication of final reports were privately provided. The data collected by each committee and checked against the combined experience of committee members and the recommendations drawn from the reports by the correlating committees were incorporated in tentative reports which were presented to a general Conference held on December 2-5, 1931.
Some 3600 people from every state in the Union as well as Hawaii and Puerto Rico were invited to Washington by the President to consider the reports and recommendations of the committees. These delegates included a wide range of individuals whose activities affected housing. In addition to the land and construction interests -realtors, sub-dividers, architects, and builders, there were manufacturers and dealers in lumber, brick, stone, concrete, tile, and what-not in the materials field; there were manufacturers of equipment and furnishings; carpenters, masons, plasterers, plumbers, and other trades; there were also the financing interests, including bankers, building and loan executives, and insurance officials; there were landscape architects, home economists, and decorators; city planners, utilities men, traffic authorities, tax experts, building inspectors, and other Government officials -State and municipal; there were, in addition, sociologists, psychologists, doctors, lawyers, educators, and editors; and there were a few -because only a few had the wide experience to be designated -housing experts. The pooling of so much experience to discuss and evaluate fact and opinion is without precedent in the history of housing. It revealed for the first time the immense scope of the subject as well as its organic unity.
To ease the serious conditions throughout the country affecting home mortgages, the President had asked the Committee on Finance and Taxation for advice on his proposal for the creation of a system of home loan discount banks. In his talk to the Conference at its first general session he explained that the proposal had been "brought forward partially to meet the situation presented by the present emergency, to alleviate the hardships that exist among home owners today, and to revitalize the building of homes as a factor of economic recovery,...in its long distance view it was put forward in the confidence that through the creation of an institution of this character we could gradually work out the problem of systematically promoted home ownership on such terms of sound finance as people who have the home-owning aspiration deserve in our country."
The Conference by unanimous resolution expressed its support of the legislation proposed by the President to create a Home Loan Bank System and to establish regional Home Loan Banks under a Federal Home Loan Bank Board. The Home Loan Bank Act (H.R. 12280) was passed by the 72nd Congress and signed by the President on July 22, 1932. The Federal Home Loan Bank Board was named on August 5. On August 9 came formal organization of the Board which promptly went to work to put the new system of banks into operations. Its major purpose was to do for institutions which lend on mortgage what the Federal Reserve system does for commercial banks. The plan was not the result of the depression but it was hurried into action by the emergencies of the depression.
The Conference provided much practical information for the whole field of housing, and Committee reports, combining the various studies, were published promptly in eleven volumes.
In addition to its specific recommendation for favorable action on the Home Loan Bank System, the Conference urged that the work of the Conference be carried on by a Constitution Committee. To some extent this follow through was handled by Better Homes in America, the staff of which could be pressed into service to handle publication of the reports. The nation-wide volunteer organization of Better Homes in America could and did make considerable effort to stimulate the utilization of the findings of the Conference.
Scope and Content
The records in this collection span the years 1926-1947, although the majority falls within the years 1931-1932, and are arranged in five series.
Most of the collection consists of COMMITTEE files, which deal with the work of the twenty-five fact-finding committees and of the six correlating committees (assigned to draw recommendations for the main committee reports).
Also important is the OFFICE FILE, related to the organization of the Conference. The areas of particular interest are the speeches of Herbert Hoover at the opening and closing ceremonies of the Conference, and his statements.
It is important to note that the REPORTS series does not include the reports themselves, but rather correspondence and memoranda related to them, as well as typescripts, galleys, forewords, lists of possible titles, and reviews of the eleven volumes put out by the Conference.
The PUBLICITY FILE covers the most extensive time-period of 1922-1947. Of special interest are the press releases which reflect the work of the Conference on a daily basis.
Afro-Americans--Housing.; Federal home loan banks.; Home ownership--United States.; Housing, Rural--United States.; Housing--United States.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Social conditions.; Urban policy--United States.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Office File, 1930-1934
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, legal documents, letters, lists, memoranda, minutes of meetings, press releases, publications, statements, summaries and other records related to the organization of the conference, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Announcement of the President's Conference Biographies. See Lists (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Board of Directors
        - Ford, James (Executive Director) (Folder 6-8)
        - Gries, John (Executive Secretary) (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Lamont, Robert (Co-chairman) (Folder 2)
        - Wilbur, Ray Lyman (President) (Folder 3-6)
      - Governors (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Mayors (Folder 2)
    - Bailey, Theodora C. (Folder 3)
    - Blanche, Halbert (Folder 4-5)
    - Bremer, Pond W. (Folder 6)
    - Chase, Pearle (Folder 7)
    - Ihlder, John (Folder 8)
    - Melvin, Bruce L. (Folder 9)
    - Richardson, Inez G. (Folder 10)
    - Saginaw, Michigan (Folder 11)
    - Taylor, James S. (Folder 12)
  - Financial records (Box 4)
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Bids (Folder 2)
    - Budgets (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with ARA Children's Fund (Folder 4)
    - Expenditures (Folder 5-7)
    - Expense voucher (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Internal Revenue Service return form (Folder 2)
    - Monthly audits of publications and postage (Folder 3)
    - Payroll (Folder 4)
    - Printing bills (Folder 5)
    - Statements (Folder 6-7)
    - Summaries (Folder 8)
    - Summaries (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Unsigned checks and statements (Folder 2-7)
    - Unsigned checks and statements (Box 7.-13.)
  - Form letters (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Index to filing cases (Folder 2)
  - Insurance file (Folder 3)
  - Inventory of supplies and equipment (Folder 4)
  - Lists
    - General. Includes biographies of all members of the President's Conference (Folder 5)
    - Appointees (Folder 6)
    - Attendees (Folder 7)
    - Colored people invited (Folder 8)
    - Committee chairmen (Folder 9)
    - Committee members
      - General
        - General (Folder 10)
        - Regional representatives (Folder 11)
      - Accepted (Folder 12)
      - Appointed by governors and mayors (Folder 13)
      - Suggested participants (Folder 14)
    - Committee personnel (Box 15)
      - General (Folder 1-2)
      - Directories (Folder 3)
    - Committees
      - Local leaders interested in home improvement (Folder 4)
      - Names for conference (Folder 5-6)
      - Registered participants (Total number, by state) (Folder 7)
      - Suggested participants (Folder 8)
  - Material for delegates (Folder 9)
  - Memoranda (Box 16)
    - General
      - Committee members (Folder 1)
      - Personnel (Folder 2)
      - Secretaries (Folder 3)
      - Staff (Folder 4)
    - Connor, Julia (Folder 5)
    - Ellington, John (Folder 6)
    - Ford, James. Includes memoranda of James S. Taylor (Folder 7)
    - Gries, John M. (Folder 8)
    - Liston, Mr. (Folder 9)
    - Ricker, George A. (Folder 10)
    - Taylor, James (Folder 11)
    - Wilbur, Ray Lyman (Folder 12)
  - Minutes of personnel meetings, 1931
    - May 13 (Folder 13)
    - May 27 (Folder 14)
    - June 19 (Folder 15)
    - July 23 (Folder 16)
  - Preliminary outline of conference (Folder 17)
  - Registration forms (Folder 18)
  - Remarks (Box 17)
    - Opening - Herbert Hoover (Honorary President) (Folder 1)
    - Closing
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 2)
      - Rippin, Deeter (Folder 3)
      - Wilbur, Ray Lyman (Folder 4)
  - Statements
    - General
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Re copyright permission (Folder 6)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1930
      - August 1 (Folder 7)
      - September 24 (Folder 8)
  - Subject file
    - Tickets (Folder 9)
    - Transportation (Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 11)
- Committees File, 1927-1933.
  Correspondence, charts, invoices, letters, lists, memoranda, messages, mimeographed material, minutes of meetings, notes, press releases, programs, questionnaires, reports, research projects, reviews, statements, arranged by type of committee and therein alphabetically by name of committee
  - General (Box 17)
    - Planning Committee. Correspondence, letters, lists of committee members, memoranda, press release, minutes of meetings
      - General (Folder 12)
      - Members (Folder 13)
      - Personnel (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Executive Committee. Stenographer's report of General session, 1931 December 2 (Folder 2)
    - Follow-Up Committee
      - General. Includes material relating to states sub-committees (Folder 3)
      - Extension program (Folder 4)
      - Fund raising file (Folder 5)
      - Letters
        - Appreciation
          - Gries, John M., to all committee members, 1931 December 26 (Folder 6)
          - Lamont, R. P., to all committee chairmen (Folder 7)
        - Replies to form letter of April 29, 1933, to all who attended the conference (Folder 8)
      - Resolution presented by the Puerto Rico Delegation (Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 10)
  - Fact finding committees
    - Blighted Areas and Slums Committee
      - General (Folder 11)
      - Correspondence - Abram Garfield, Chairman (Folder 12)
      - Financial records (Folder 13)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1931 (Box 19)
        - June 16 (Folder 1)
        - July 13 (Folder 2)
        - September 24 (Folder 3)
        - October 26-27 (Folder 4)
    - Business and Housing Committee
      - Correspondence (Folder 5)
      - Drafts of resolution for presentation to the Committee
        - Kohler, Walter J. (Folder 6)
        - Wetherill, Samuel P. (Folder 7)
      - Lists of committee members
        - Suggested (Folder 8)
        - Final (Folder 9)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1931
        - September 18 (Folder 10)
        - September 29 (Folder 11)
      - Reports
        - First draft of report for the committee (Ely, Richard) (Folder 12)
        - Final report of the committee (Folder 13)
    - City Planning and Zoning Committee
      - General (Folder 14)
      - Clippings (Folder 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 16)
      - Financial records (Folder 17)
      - Lists of committee members (Folder 18)
      - Memoranda (Folder 19)
      - Regional planning notes (Folder 20)
      - Reports
        - 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 21)
        - 1932 January 20 (MacDougall, Edward A.) (Folder 22)
    - Construction Committee (Box 20)
      - Correspondence - Gries, John M. (Folder 1)
      - Financial records (Folder 2)
      - Memoranda (Folder 3)
      - Stenographer's report of the committee of construction, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 4)
    - Design Committee
      - Correspondence - Parker, William Stanley (Folder 5)
      - Financial records (Folder 6)
      - Lists of committee members (Folder 7)
      - Stenographer's report, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 8)
    - Farm and Village Housing Committee
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Circular letters (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence
        - General. Regarding approvals of publications (Folder 11)
        - Ford, James (Folder 12)
        - Mann, Albert R. (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
        - Melvin, Bruce (Folder 3)
      - Financial records (Folder 4)
      - Lists of committee members (Folder 5)
      - Memoranda (Folder 6)
      - Proposals
        - Cooperative farm colony (Folder 7)
        - Housing of Mexicans and Indians (Folder 8)
        - Indian housing improvement (Folder 9)
        - Organization of an agricultural service corporation (Folder 10)
      - Publicity file (Folder 11)
      - Radio interview with Bruce L. Melvin, Research Secretary of the committee (Folder 12)
      - Reports
        - Stenographer's report, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 13)
        - Work of the committee (Folder 14)
      - Scale for rating living room equipment (Folder 15)
      - Score cards
        - Dwelling house (Folder 16)
        - Home grounds (Folder 17)
    - Finance Committee
      - General (Folder 18)
      - Address made by Frederick Ecker, Vice-President, 1919 December 4-5 (Folder 19)
      - Correspondence. Mostly of Frederick H. Ecker (Folder 20)
      - Division mortgage structure (Folder 21)
      - Editorial file (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Invoices (Folder 2)
      - Lists
        - Attendees of the conference (Folder 3)
        - Possible members (Folder 4)
        - Members (final list) (Folder 5)
      - Memoranda (Folder 6)
      - Reports, 1931
        - November 14 (related to foreclosure laws and foreclosure provisions) (Folder 7)
        - November 15 (report and recommendations) (Folder 8)
        - 1931 December 2-5 (stenographer's) (Folder 9)
        - 1931 December 4 (tentative report) (Folder 10)
      - Statement by Herbert Hoover, 1931 November 13 (Folder 11)
      - Statistics (Folder 12)
      - Suggestions for program of the committee (Folder 13)
    - Fundamental Equipment Committee
      - General (Folder 14)
      - Agenda of meeting, 1931 July 17 (Folder 15)
      - Article on talk given by George N. Thompson, 1932 April 30 (Folder 16)
      - Correspondence. Mostly of Collins P. Bliss, Chairman (Folder 17)
      - Endorsement of report, 1932 February (Folder 18)
      - Invoices (Folder 19)
      - Lists
        - Committee members (Folder 20)
        - Subdivisions (Folder 21)
      - Memoranda (Folder 22)
      - Statement by Dr. James Ford regarding the scope of work, 1931 (Folder 23)
      - Stenographer's report of meetings, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 24)
    - Home Furnishing and Decoration Committee
      - Endorsement of report, 1931 November (Folder 25)
      - Invoices (Folder 26)
      - Stenographer's report of meetings, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 27)
    - Home Information Centers Committee (Box 23)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Brief summary of procedure (Folder 2)
      - Correspondence
        - Chase, Pearl. Includes excerpts of a letter from Henry Wright, Research Secretary, Committee on Design, to Pearl Chase (Folder 3-4)
        - Ford, James (Folder 5)
        - Frampton, Merle E. (Folder 6)
        - Gries, John, M. (Folder 7)
        - Hall, Marion (Folder 8)
        - Kelley, Roy H. (Folder 9)
        - Merrill, Julia Wright (Folder 10)
        - Miscellany (Folder 11)
      - Editorial file (Folder 12)
      - Invoices (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Letters (Folder 2)
      - Lists
        - Agencies (commercial, educational, and social) to receive Miss Atwater's questionnaire (Folder 3)
        - Committee's findings as to the how, why, who, and what of the Home Information Services (Folder 4)
        - Existing agencies in Boston involved in homemaking (Folder 5)
        - Members of the committee. Includes correspondence (Folder 6-7)
        - Officers in departments of education in charge of adult education (Folder 8)
        - Plan service organizations (Folder 9)
      - Memoranda. Includes regulations and by-laws of American Home Information Service (Folder 10)
      - Mimeographed material (Folder 11)
      - Mimeographed material (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1931
        - June 9-10 (Folder 2)
        - September 24-26 (Folder 3)
      - Notes
        - Meeting of section B of the Committee, 1931 August 29 (Folder 4)
        - Parker, Mr. (Folder 5)
      - Plans re possible organization (Folder 6)
      - Program (Folder 7)
      - Publicity files. Include illustrative material (Folder 8-9)
      - Questionnaires
        - Agencies giving public information (Folder 10)
        - Home building clinic (Folder 11)
        - Local organizations (Folder 12)
      - Recommendations (Box 26)
        - For the committee (Folder 1)
        - Of the committee (Folder 2)
      - Reports
        - General
          - Undated (Folder 3)
          - 1931
            - General (Folder 4)
            - September 25 (supplementary) (Folder 5)
            - September 30 (summarized) (Folder 6)
            - December 2-5 (stenographer's) (Folder 7)
        - On Home Information Centers directed by or affiliated with American Homemakers, Inc. (Folder 8)
        - On publicity program (Folder 9)
      - Scope sheet (Folder 10)
      - Studies
        - Building material exhibits, 1931 September (Folder 11)
        - Providence, RI, by Ida S. Harrington, 1931 September (Folder 12)
        - Twenty-four selected cities (Folder 13)
      - Subject file
        - General (Folder 14)
        - Exhibits (Folder 15)
        - Salt Lake City (Folder 16)
        - Santa Barbara (Folder 17)
      - Suggestions
        - General (Folder 18)
        - For a National Institute of Housing and Civic Affairs, 1931 September 23 (Folder 19)
        - From Bleeker Marquette, 1931 September 18 (Folder 20)
    - Home Ownership and Leasing Committee
      - General (Folder 21)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 22)
        - Gries, John M. (Folder 23)
        - Trigg, Ernest T. (Folder 24)
      - List of committee members (Folder 25)
      - Memoranda (Folder 26)
      - Program (Folder 27)
      - Regional survey of New York and its environs (Folder 28)
      - Reports
        - Preliminary draft of a report of the Committee, 1931 October 12 (Folder 29)
        - Stenographic, 1931 December 4 (Folder 30)
    - Homemaking Committee
      - General (Folder 31)
      - Correspondence
        - General (Folder 32)
        - Van Rensselaer, Martha (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 2)
      - Editorial file (Folder 3)
      - Invoices (Folder 4)
      - Lists
        - Agencies in Boston related to homemaking (Folder 5)
        - Members
          - Committee (Folder 6)
          - Sub-committee (Folder 7)
      - Memoranda (Folder 8)
      - Minutes of meeting, 1931 August 1 (Folder 9)
      - Press release, 1931 December 5 (Folder 10)
      - Questionnaire replies (Folder 11)
      - Reports
        - General
          - Brief (on the Alabama study) (Folder 12)
          - Main. Includes endorsements (Folder 13)
          - Stenographer's, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 14)
          - Tentative (Folder 15)
        - Sub-committees on city housing and family development
          - General
            - 1931 September 29 (Folder 16)
            - 1931 December 5 (Folder 17)
          - Preliminary on special problems of city living (Folder 18)
          - Research (Folder 19)
          - Supplementary, 1931 December 5 (Folder 20)
    - Household Management Committee (Box 28)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Correspondence
        - Ford, James (Folder 2)
        - Gries, John (Folder 3)
        - Raitt, Effie I. (Folder 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
      - List of committee members (Folder 6)
      - Memoranda (Folder 7)
      - Preliminary notes on meeting, 1931 July 1 (Folder 8)
      - Stenographer's report, 1931 December 2-5 (Folder 9)
    - Housing and the Community Committee
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence
        - Cabot, Richard Clarke (Folder 11)
        - Ford, James (Folder 12)
        - Gries, John (Folder 13)
        - Pratt, Joseph H. (Folder 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 15)